hey everyone welcome back to another
lesson in this tosa automation playlist
today we are going to talk about the
dynamic datea Expressions which are
present in tosa and how you can use them
in several scenarios where you need to
perform some date calculations so let's
look at one such field now I am in the
TR centers vehicle uh demo application
and here you can see we need to enter
some start date here right and enter
product data screen now I have entered
one date here uh which is the starting
date for this year but it gives a error
message saying it must be more than one
month in the future right so this date
should always be one month more than the
current date okay so if I calculate the
date okay it should be something like
2023 or uh 11
2023 okay also uh it accepts the date in
the mmddyy format and that's why this
error was still coming because I have
entered it in the wrong format so I need
to make it 11 17 and then 2023 okay so
now uh the date is validated and it's
correct now in these type of scenarios
you cannot just enter any particular
date you have to enter a date which
satisfies this condition which is
mentioned for this particular field and
even though you have uh stored some
dates like some sample dates in your
test sheet and you try to enter it into
this particular field it might work on
that same day but it may not work the
next day because the calculation
would go wrong right so this kind of
test data cannot be uh static in nature
so you cannot store static test data it
has to be dynamic in nature so you need
to put some calculation before you enter
something in this particular field so
let's see how we can use the dynamic
data expression in this particular case
and how we can perform this calculation
where we need to enter a date which is
one month in future
so uh let's uh head back to tosa and
here I have already scanned this
particular module okay uh so I have
recorded this uh date field which is a
start date and then I have created a
test case where I'm using this
particular module
okay now one way is I can directly enter
the date here right it is a text field
but uh you know it will not work right
maybe it will work today but but
tomorrow it won't work because again it
won't be one month in the future right
so we need to use something called the
date expression in this value field okay
and the date expression can be found uh
when you start your curly Braes you will
find it in the drop down okay and there
is something called
Date okay and there's also a date time
expression if you want to use that time
now for this date uh it will return you
the full current date okay uh and you
can see here the date and time values
can be calculated by using the base date
along with deviations and it can be
displayed in a user defined format okay
so it can do all of this it can
calculate the date based on a base date
uh along with some deviations so you can
do some calculations and then it can
also be displayed in a particular format
okay so the Syntax for this is here so
in date we need to provide a base date
okay it could be any date and then you
need to provide the offset now offset is
something uh called the deviation from
the base date so either you can add some
days to your base date or you can
subtract some days from the base date uh
now this uh offset it could be in months
it could be in days it could be in weeks
um or it could be in several other
variations
okay and also we can uh Define the
format okay so the date expression
format of the test object can be defined
here there's also an example here you
can see so there is the datea expression
then there is the base date which is 23
uh May
2016 then here is the offset which which
is here we are calculating plus 3 months
which is uh it will calculate uh 3
months in future for this particular
date and then it will also minus one day
okay so this is the calculation which it
is doing and then here it is specifying
the format which is
mmddyy y okay and then the result is
this so we need uh something similar
here in our scenario we need need to um
find out the date 1 month in future so
let's uh now enter um our value here
which is one month in future okay it is
pretty similar so we'll start off with
the square brackets and then I'm going
to close the square brackets now you
need to make sure that even though
you're not mentioning any value you
should always follow the syntax which
means there should be always three
square brackets no matter which one you
are providing the values or which you
are not providing the values okay now I
don't want to enter any particular uh
base date value here because by default
the base date is the current date and
that works for me because I want to
calculate based on my current date now
if your calculation is based on a
particular date then you can mention the
base date as that date okay and then the
calculation will be done on that base
date okay so for me it is the current
date and that's why I have not mention
anything now I will do the calculation
which is the offset so I want plus one
month and also I want plus 1D which is
1D okay and that is because uh in here
you will see that if I mention just one
month in future it won't satisfy the
condition it should be 1 month in future
plus one day okay which is the next day
so I'm going to enter this and then it
will be satisfied right also you can see
the format is MM DD and yyy so I need to
provide or the date in this particular
format
okay so in the last field it is for the
format and I'm going to now mention mm
and then I'm going to mention slash
okay and DD and then again slash and
then YY y so this is the
format uh which should be calculated
okay also we need to end the clyra here
and it should look like
this now if I translate this particular
value you will see that the translation
was successful and my value is exactly
what I want which is 1117
2023 now the advantage of uh taking this
calculation or picking up a dynamic
expression is tomorrow right if I
execute this it will again change the
date based on the calculation so every
day the value would be different and it
will satisfy the condition and that's
how my test case will never fail right
so that's the uh importance of having a
dynamic value instead of a static value
okay so now if I run this in
scratchbook okay so it should enter the
date and then the date will be
validated so uh this is how you can use
the dynamic date expression which is
available in tosa for Fields where you
require some offset or some ad
adjustments to your current date or some
particular date okay so some condition
needs to be satisfied before you enter
some value in that particular field and
it is dynamically changing okay so this
is where you can make use of the dynamic
data expression and there are lots of
different options in the dynamic data
expressions in
tosa that's all for this particular
video if you have any questions then
please leave it in the comments if you
like this video then please subscribe to
our Channel thanks for watching and I
will see you in the next video